Today's דף נה, Daf nun hey, 55. We're actually a little ahead.
We pick up right before the משנה, Mishnah, about ten lines down.
We're ending a discussion about issues around adding a חומש chomesh for
מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, for הקדש, Hekdesh, for other types of things,
which we sort of got to after a sort of little bit
of a digression about talking about issues of אונאה. Ona'ah. But we're
going to see very soon that that actually is going to be
a focus of the משניות Mishnayot coming up. So let's take a
look now about right after they quote the פסוק העולה, Pasuk ha'Olah,
says ויקרא ו Vayikra vav in the right-hand margin between the גמרא
Gemara and רש"י. Rashi. It says תניא כוותיה דרבי יהושע בן לוי.
Tanya k'vatei d'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. We taught like רבי יהושע בן
לוי. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. What did רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi say? He said that the הלכה halacha is that
you only add a חומש chomesh when you transfer from something sanctified
the first time, but the second generation, after it's already been transferred
and you go from that money to other money, you do not
add a חומש. chomesh. So תניא כוותיה דרבי יהושע בן לוי, Tanya
k'vatei d'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, פרה זו תחת פרה של הקדש טלית
זו תחת טלית של הקדש הקדשו פדוי ויד הקדש על העליונה. Para
zo tachat para shel Hekdesh, tallis zo tachat tallis shel Hekdesh, Hekdesho
paduy v'yad Hekdesh al ha'elyona. If you say this cow in exchange
for this הקדש Hekdesh cow, or this טלית tallis in exchange for
this הקדש Hekdesh טלית, tallis, so then it works. You don't have
to do it on money; you can do it on objects. And
הקדש Hekdesh has the upper hand. What does it mean הקדש Hekdesh
has the upper hand? If the second object is worth less than
the first, then you still owe הקדש Hekdesh the difference. Since, although
as תוספות Tosafot points out, there's a famous הלכה halacha of שמואל
Shmuel that even if you took הקדש Hekdesh worth a thousand dollars
and transferred it to a פרוטה, prutah, a penny, it works, because
actually when you're transferring קדושה, Kedushah, you're sort of doing two things.
One is the aspect about that this is הקדש's Hekdesh property. So,
and like, so you're taking some value away from הקדש, Hekdesh, you
have to replace that. So that's obviously why you have to do
the equal value. But the other way you could look at it
is you're just transferring status. So if you're just transferring status, you
take something of a thousand dollars, it doesn't matter, you think about
it as just קדושה Kedushah as an abstract status. So you move
the קדושה Kedushah from one object, you put it in another. So
שמואל Shmuel actually says בדיעבד b'dieved that works, but nevertheless even if
it's not of equal value. But nevertheless, you, so that's certainly not
the default and certainly not what we assume you're trying to do
unless you make that explicit. So therefore if you say this cow
in exchange for this cow, it works, but if the second cow
is not worth as much, you owe הקדש Hekdesh the difference. If,
however, the second cow is worth more, הקדש Hekdesh gets the whole
cow. So therefore, you know, it's like because you didn't specify, הקדש
Hekdesh always gets the benefit of the doubt. It's assumed that you
don't want to do less than its value, but if it actually
was worth more than its value and you said a cow for
a cow, so it's assumed you want to give the whole cow
to הקדש. Hekdesh. However, if you say פרה זו בחמש סלעים תחת
פרה של הקדש, Para zo b'chamesh sela'im tachat para shel Hekdesh,
this cow, which I know is worth five סלעים, sela'im, is in
exchange for this הקדש Hekdesh cow, or טלית זו בחמש סלעים, tallis
zo b'chamesh sela'im, or this טלית, tallis, you know, because of its
five dollar value is תחת טלית של הקדש, tachat tallis shel Hekdesh,
which means basically you're saying that the הקדש Hekdesh object is worth
five dollars and because you're saying that the second object is worth
five dollars, you're transferring the קדושה, Kedushah, הקדשו פדוי, Hekdesho paduy,
it works. But it's not יד הקדש על העליונה. yad Hekdesh al
ha'elyona. Now just read the end and I'll go back and explain
that. על הקדש ראשון מוסיף חומש על הקדש שני אין מוסיף חומש.
Al Hekdesh rishon mosif chomesh, al Hekdesh sheni ein mosif chomesh. So
that was the reason we were quoting it, because that is like
רבי יהושע בן לוי. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. For if you go
from the, when you transfer from the first cow to the second,
you add a חומש, chomesh, right? But if you're transferring from the
second cow to something else, you don't add a חומש. chomesh. Okay,
so that's the basic point that you only add a חומש chomesh
for first generation, not second generation. But the difficulty of the second
one is in the second one where you're not saying a cow
for a cow, you're saying it's worth five dollars or whatever. So
therefore in that case, if it's, if for whatever reason the second
thing is
not, if take a look here, let's read תוספות, Tosafot, he spells
it out. תוספות Tosafot says the following: טלית זו בחמש סלעים הקדשו
פדוי. Tallis zo b'chamesh sela'im Hekdesho paduy.
If you look at that תוספות טלית, Tosafot Tallis, he says הכא
לא גרסינן יד הקדש על העליונה דכיון שנתכוין לחלל הקדש אפילו שוה
הרבה על דבר מועט מחולל. Hacha lo garsinan yad Hekdesh al ha'elyona,
d'keivan she'nitkavein l'challel Hekdesh, afilu shaveh harbeh al davar muat, mechullal.
So here, because you're saying this הקדש Hekdesh is exchanged for this
thing that's worth five dollars, even if the original הקדש Hekdesh was
worth a thousand dollars, as I said to you before, if you
explicitly state that I'm going to do something worth a lot on
something worth a little, it works. So since you're saying I know
that this second thing is only worth five dollars, okay, then even
if the first thing was worth more, you are explicitly transferring it
on less and therefore it works and הקדש Hekdesh does not, you
don't owe הקדש Hekdesh the difference. כדיקאמר שמואל לקמן. K'dikmar Shmuel lekaman.
אבל ברישא שלא הזכיר שום שוה, Aval b'reisha shelo hizkir shum shaveh,
but in the first case when you just said a cow for
a cow or this טלית tallis for this טלית, tallis, לא היה
בדעתו לקנות הקדש. lo haya b'daato liknot Hekdesh. your language reflects that
you wanted to do an equal exchange. וכך ישלים *vekach yoshlim*. And
therefore if the second thing was worth less, because your language says
a טס *tas* for a טלית *tallis*, we're going to assume that
that means you want to exchange an equivalent amount and if there
is a difference, you'll pay the difference. So one way in which
the second case is not יד הקדש hekdesh על העליונה *yad hekdesh
al ha-elyona* is if the second thing is worth less, הקדש hekdesh?
*hekdesh* loses out because you're making it say like I know that
it's only worth five and I'm transferring it on this value. Similarly
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says ואם הותיר יד הקדש hekdesh על העליונה *ve-im
hotir yad hekdesh al ha-elyona* לכך לא עירב לשון שניהם כאחד *lekach
lo eirev leshon sheneihem ke-echad*. Similarly, if the second thing is worth
more, in the first case you're saying a cow for a cow,
so we assume you mean whatever this second cow is worth, even
if it's worth more. Whereas in the whereas in the second case
when you say this for five dollars, you're only transferring it onto
five dollars of the cow or you know you're not transferring it
onto you know if the second cow is worth more than five.
What happens if the thing is really worth six? You mean you
misquoted the value? Yeah, I don't know I don't know if you
interpret the word בחמש סלעים *be-chamesh sela-im* means five dollars of its
value or you're claiming that it's only worth five. I think it
means five dollars of its value and therefore you're being very explicit
in both directions, right? You're saying that I'm not giving the whole
cow, I'm only giving five dollars of the value. So if the
whole cow is worth more, too bad, I'm only transferring it on
five dollars of the value. And number two is even if I
know that this thing is even if the הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* was
worth more, I know that this is only worth five dollars and
that's all I'm giving to הקדש hekdesh, *hekdesh*. What do you do
practically? Like I'm doing it on this watch which is worth five
dollars and it's worth eight hundred dollars. Like would I have to
sell the watch and then... Yeah, הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* is a partner
in the watch. So yeah. Alright now the other interesting thing I
wanted to say is how can you do a cow on a
cow? Isn't that an explicit הלכה halacha, *halacha* in the תורה Torah,
*Torah* of תמורה *tmura* of והיה הוא ותמורתו יהיה קדש *ve-haya hu
u-tmurato yiheyeh kodesh* that it doesn't work? Okay, so take a look
at תוספות Tosafot. *Tosafot* well right. So take a look at תוספות
Tosafot, *Tosafot* פרה זו תחת פרה של הקדש hekdesh הקדש hekdesh פדויה
*para zu tachat para shel hekdesh hekdesh peduya*. So it says ואם
תאמר והכתיב *ve-im tomar ve-haktiv* I love this, he's quoting from a
פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. How can you say this? What about a פסוק
pasuk? *pasuk*? It says והיה הוא ותמורתו יהיה קדש *ve-haya hu u-tmurato
yiheyeh kodesh*. So how it doesn't work, a cow on a cow.
יש לומר דהכא במאי עסקינן בקדשי בדק הבית *yesh lomar de-hacha be-mai
askinan be-kodshei bedek ha-bayit*. Okay, it's by it's something that belongs to
the הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* treasury. That when is it that you try
to transfer from one to another, you it doesn't work? That's called
תמורה *tmura*. That's only when the first thing is a קרבן korban,
*korban* or maybe it's even a קרבן korban *korban* with a מום
*mum*, but basically it's the קדושה kedusha, *kedusha* of a קרבן korban
*korban*. And in that case, you can only you can't transfer at
all if it doesn't have a מום *mum*, and even if it
does have a מום *mum*, you can really only transfer onto money.
But when you're dealing with something which is קדשי בדק הבית *kodshei
bedek ha-bayit*, you treat everything as just an object. You know, it's
really just about the value. So therefore since it's just about the
value, it's not a sense of like intrinsic קדושה *kedusha*. By something
that's a קרבן korban. *korban*, it's like this purpose of this is
to be brought as a קרבן korban *korban*. And that's why you've
only special rules when you can sort of remove that קדושה *kedusha*.
But for something you're basically giving as a donation, the base point
of it is about its value and for it to be sold
and therefore you can transfer even from like a cow to a
cow. Okay, so תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* discusses some of those specifics. Yes.
In the earlier תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* the very last line it says
ולא איצטריך לשנות הבבות *velo itztarich lishnot ha-babot* it means that's why
you need the רישא *reisha* to sit with the... Right, that's why
it said it and didn't say it in the... right because one
is יד הקדש hekdesh על העליונה *yad hekdesh al ha-elyona* and the
other is not, correct. Okay. Yeah. Okay. So anyway so now we
look at the next משנה Mishnah, *mishnah*
Toby, I think that might be done, can you see? Okay. האונאה
ארבעה כסף kessef *ha-ona-ah arba-ah kessef*. So now
we have mentioned in a previous משנה Mishnah, *mishnah*, so now we're
going to go back and repeat this in order to get to
the end of this, but we're pulling some things together. Okay, that
overcharging is ארבעה כסף kessef *arba-ah kessef* per סלע sela *sela*, which
is basically, you know, which he said one-sixth. והטענה שתי כסף kessef
*ve-ha-ta-ana shtei kessef*. If you make a claim against somebody, this is
for מודה במקצת modeh bemiktzat *modeh be-miktzat*. The claim against the person,
you know, he admits to part of it, then he takes a
שבועה shvuah *shevua* about the rest. So that the admission is only
an admission only has to be an admission of a פרוטה perutah
*pruta* or the denial only has to be a denial of a
פרוטה perutah *pruta*. But the original claim has to be שתי כסף
kessef *shtei kessef*, which is שתי מעה ma'ah. *shtei ma-ah*. Meaning when
you admit the other he denies, I'm sorry what was the...? You
claim you owe me שתי מעה ma'ah *shtei ma-ah*, which is I
don't know how many פרוטות perutot. *prutos*, let's say a hundred פרוטות
perutot. *prutos* let's say, I don't know, I forgot the math. Okay,
we could do the math. But anyway, and then you for you
to be a מודה במקצת modeh bemiktzat. *modeh be-miktzat*, you can either
say yes I owe you all of that except one פרוטה perutah
*pruta*, you're lying about one פרוטה perutah *pruta*, or you can say
no I don't owe you any of that but I do owe
you one פרוטה perutah *pruta*. So any any range between admitting to
one פרוטה perutah *pruta* to you know and denying everything else to
denying one פרוטה perutah *pruta* and admitting everything else is enough for
you to make a מודה במקצת modeh bemiktzat *modeh be-miktzat*. But if
you deny less than a פרוטה perutah. *pruta* or you admit less
than a פרוטה perutah *pruta*, then you don't make a שבועה shvuah
*shevua*. But that's your admission or denial, my initial claim has to
be for שתי מעה ma'ah. *shtei ma-ah*. Okay, so the same so
that's just a הלכה halacha *halacha* about how big my initial claim
has to be. Wait, why is four one-sixth, how does that...? Because
because a סלע sela, *sela* out of a סלע selah. *sela* and
a סלע selah, *sela* is twenty-four מעה ma'ah, *ma-ah*. Oh, okay. So
וההודאה שוה פרוטה shaveh prutah *ve-ha-hoda-ah shaveh pruta*. So the admission has
to be an admission of a פרוטה perutah. *pruta*, the initial claim
has to be the שתי מעה ma'ah *shtei ma-ah*. חמש פרוטות הן
chamesh perutot hen, *chamesh prutos hen*. There are five places where פרוטה
perutah *pruta* matters. הודאה שוה פרוטה perutah. *hoda-ah shaveh pruta*, admission to
a claim so that it becomes a מודה במקצת modeh b'miktzas, *modeh
be-miktzat*, you have to... At least a פרוטה. perutah. והאשה מתקדשת בשוה
פרוטה, vehaishah mitkadeshet bishvei perutah, a woman can be married with a
פרוטה perutah according to בית הלל. Beit Hillel.
והנהנה
בשוה פרוטה מן ההקדש מעל, vehahaneh bishvei perutah min hahekdesh ma'al, so
there we just touched on מעילה me'ilah before by the fifth. If
you get a פרוטה perutah of benefit from הקדש hekdesh, you did
מעילה, me'ilah, less than that not. והמוצא שוה פרוטה חייב להכריז vehamotzei
shaveh perutah chayav lehachriz and going back to an earlier פרק, perek,
if you find something worth a פרוטה perutah. you have to announce
it and return it to the owner. והגוזל חברו שוה פרוטה vehagozel
chavero shaveh perutah going back to בבא קמא Bava Kamma הלכה, halacha
if you steal something worth a פרוטה perutah, ונשבע לו venishba lo
and you swear falsely, then יוליכנו אחריו אפילו למדי, yolichenu acharav afilu
leMadai, you have to return it to him even if he's halfway
around the world and you have to return it directly to him.
Less than that you don't have to chase him. Okay, so all
these things in which basically a פרוטה perutah. defines a minimum amount
of money. By the way, the מעילה me'ilah question is not necessarily
as obvious as you would have imagined because there's a question about
whether you conceptualize מעילה me'ilah as a type of a stealing, and
if you conceptualize it as a type of a stealing then פרוטה
pruta, makes sense because that's a minimum definition of money. Or do
you conceptualize מעילה me'ilah as a type of inappropriate benefiting from
הקדש? If I benefit, well maybe I don't know, let's say I
ate something of הקדש that was כזית, kezayit, but let's say it
wasn't a פרוטה pruta worth, right? Is it because basically I did
this act of
deriving physical
benefit or is it about taking something of value? So that's like
interesting. So here the הלכה Halacha is that it is a פרוטה.
pruta. Now but here the הלכה by מעילה me'ilah is clear, but
an interesting case where there actually is a debate is let's say
you have something that's אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. Let's say you have
בשר בחלב basar bechalav that's אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah or
let's say you have עבודה זרה avodah zarah that's אסור בהנאה assur
behana'ah or something of that nature. Okay, how much do I have
to benefit in order to be deserving of מלקות? malkus? A פרוטה's
pruta. worth or a כזית kezayit worth? It's an interesting debate of
the אחרונים acharonim whether you think about הנאה hana'ah as a type
of an אכילה, achilah, right? So therefore you focus on כזית kezayit
or do you think about it as different, as like monetary benefit,
gain, and therefore it's a פרוטה. pruta. Anyway, but here all these
things are defined in terms of money and therefore פרוטה Pruta. is
the minimum. So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. תנינא
חדא זימנא. tanina chada zimna. Who needs to teach you the first
line about אונאה? ona'ah? We taught that in an earlier משנה, Mishnah.
in this פרק perek let alone. האונאה ארבע כסף מעשרים וארבע כסף
לסלע, ha'ona'ah arba kessef me'esrim ve'arba kessef lesela, אונאה ona'ah is four
כסף kessef out of a סלע selah. worth 24 מעה. ma'ah So
that's one-sixth, שתות למקח, shtus lemekach, a
sixth. התנא שתי כסף, hatana shtei kessef, we want to get to
the rest of the משנה, Mishnah. that's our hook to get to
the rest of the משנה. Mishnah והודאת שוה פרוטה איצטריכא ליה, vehoda'at
shaveh perutah itztricha lei, to tell you another case where כסף kessef
matters, where מעה ma'ah, matters. Not four but two, that the claim
of מודה במקצת modeh b'miktzas is has to be two מעה. ma'ah.
So the גמרא Gemara says הנמי תנינא, ha nami tanina, that's also
a משנה. Mishnah Not here but in שבועות. Shevuot. שבועות הדיינים, Shevuot
Hadayanim, right, exactly, שבועות הדיינים, Shevuot Hadayanim, but so far if it's
all we're doing is repeating there's no purpose. שבועות הדיינים, Shevuot Hadayanim,
so when you come to a type of a שבועה that judges
will impose and a שבועה of a מודה במקצת. modeh b'miktzas הטענה
שתי כסף והודאה שוה פרוטה. hata'anah shtei kessef vehoda'ah shaveh perutah. The
original claim has to be two כסף and you have to admit
to at least a פרוטה. pruta So it says סיפא איצטריכא ליה.
seifa itztricha lei. You're right, that also wasn't necessary, but that hook
one was to get to hook two and hook two was to
get to the end of the משנה Mishnah, which was חמש פרוטות
הן, chamesh perutot hen. that there are five פרוטות. perutot. You realize
why you needed that, right? Because the second thing
about the מודה במקצת brought in the idea of a פרוטה. pruta.
So since until now we've been talking about מעה, ma'ah like we
had a whole other משנה Mishnah about how much is a coin
like lacking, right,
1/24th, 1/48th, 1/12th, 1/6th, whatever, 1/24th, so we're talking about all these
questions about minimum
value. So talking about four מעה ma'ah lets us get to the
טענה ta'anah of two מעה ma'ah, which brings in the idea of
a פרוטה pruta which now lets us get to talking about פרוטות.
perutot So the טענה ta'anah has to be two because so that
the admission is מקצת? miktzat? No, because it's two מעה, ma'ah it's
not two פרוטות. perutot, I mean if you want me, I don't
remember exactly, I'll tell you what roughly what I think it is.
I'll go back and look at a previous רש"י. Rashi. א מעה
a ma'ah was,
let's take a look, א מעה a ma'ah was two פונדיון, pundeyon,
א פונדיון a pundeyon was two איסר issar and a פרוטה pruta,
is one-eighth of an איסר. issar. So that's two, four, 32,
32 פרוטות perutot per מעה. ma'ah, So it's when you demand two
מעה ma'ah that's 64 פרוטות, perutot? okay? So your initial demand has
to be 64 פרוטות perutot and the admission has to be one
פרוטה. pruta Why can't it just be two פרוטות? perutot Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara if we were learning שבועות Shevuot the גמרא Gemara
would learn that out but that's not what we're learning right now.
So we're going to focus on the second part of the משנה,
Mishnah, okay? So the part about the פרוטות perutot which is not
taught elsewhere.
חמש פרוטות הן. chamesh prutos hein. וליתני נמי האונאה פרוטה. velisni nami
ha'ona'ah perutah. Okay, now, now we're going to ask interesting questions, what's
not on the list? So we said that the אונאה ona'ah is
one-sixth, okay, two מעה ma'ah per סלע, sela but let's say you're
something that's worth six פרוטות prutos. and you overcharged a guy one
פרוטה, perutah, that should also be אונאה. ona'ah. Now let's say something
was worth three פרוטות prutos. and you overcharged them a half a
פרוטה. perutah That's not אונאה, ona'ah, that's not a question of. proportion
of ratio, that's the question of minimum amount, right? If something is
less than a פרוטה, perutah. it's like it's not—it doesn't even count
as money. So why did not we say in addition to the
question of ratio and proportion of אונאה ona'ah that the minimum amount
for something to be considered אונאה ona'ah is a פרוטה's perutah worth?
That's a good question. So the גמרא Gemara says וניתני נמי אונאה
פרוטה. v'nitni nami ona'ah pruta. אמר רב כהנא Amar Rav Kahana זאת
אומרת אין אונאה לפרוטות. zot omeret ein ona'ah l'prutos.
That actually,
there is no אונאה—thank ona'ah you so much, I really need that
this morning.
There is no אונאה ona'ah if something is, you know, for like
pennies. אונאה Ona'ah is even a higher minimum amount than פרוטה. perutah
You know, how much is the minimum amount? So if you look
at רשי, Rashi, ופחות מאיסר שהוא מטבע של כסף. u'pachos mi'isar she'hu
matbea shel kesef.
Anything less than an איסר, isar, right? So I told you what
was it, which is interesting, because like I don't know who told
רשי Rashi that, but okay, but you know, it is, maybe because...
so a מעה, ma'ah right, there are six מעות ma'os to a
דינר. dinar. And by the way, just you know, when you throw
it up that high people watching can't see it.
All right.
Very sensitive to all our watchers. Okay. So there are six מעה
ma'ah
per
דינר, dinar, okay? And that's how you know it's one מעה, ma'ah
it's like a total
of four, you know, and there are four דינר dinar per סלע.
sela
Okay. So anyway, it was one מעה ma'ah basically, that's why
it was four מעה ma'ah per סלע, sela one מעה per דינר.
dinar. So one מעה per דינר dinar is a one-to-six. Okay? And
then anyway, מעה is two
פונדיון. pundiyon. Is that right? Yeah, פונדיון. pundiyon. And a פונדיון pundiyon
is two איסר. isar. And an איסר isar is
eight—okay, so that's two, two, and that's eight פרוטות. prutos. Okay. So
anyway, so רשי Rashi tells you that איסר isar is the last
thing out of silver. All right? So anyway, so the normal sort
of thing was one מעה per סלע. sela, Anyway, that's a one
מעה per דינר dinar was a six-to-one ratio, but the minimum amount
of overcharge that matters is an איסר's isar worth of overcharge, eight
times a פרוטה. perutah. Once you get to the copper that's sort
of so trivial that even if it was—even if I charged you,
I don't know, you know, like you go into a, you know,
I charge you like ten cents for a five-cent piece of gum,
okay, that's not אונאה, ona'ah, it's only five cents. Okay. When once
it's that small amount total, it doesn't count. Only when it's sort
of a certain minimum amount, not only a minimum ratio. Okay. So
רשי Rashi says that to איסר. isar. Yeah. But you know, we
have a whole thing about the גזל שוה פרוטה. gezel shaveh pruta.
גזל שוה פרוטה, Gezel shaveh pruta, I know. But the words—you're right.
Meaning גזילה gezeilah is a פרוטה. perutah... And that's what the early
rest of the משנה Mishnah. says. So it's not like in general
it doesn't count as money, but in terms of overcharge,
you know, for whatever reason overcharge is not just a function of
ratio. It's like you actually bought something with your money, I didn't
take it away from you, right? So a few extra pennies, even
though proportionally it's a lot more than it's worth, right, it's like
big deal. I mean I think you feel that way, right? I
don't know, I feel that way. Like, okay, wow, he charged me
a dime for a five-cent piece of gum. Do I really care
so much? You know, okay. Anyway, all right. So moving on. Although
I do want to say yesterday I was at the Met exhibit,
last night I was at the Met exhibit in
on Jerusalem, a lot of it was not from things from Jerusalem
but were evocative of Jerusalem and a lot of things weren't Jewish
and where but of course because Jerusalem wasn't just Jewish. But I
did want to show you this. You know what those are? פרוטה.
prutah. Gold דינרי. dinarei.
Each one of those is worth twenty-five silver דינר. dinar. Okay. Some
of these, the smaller ones, are an eighth of a gold דינר.
dinar. So anyway, so that's it, right in the piles that are
scraped below the ones that you can actually... Yeah, right. Anyway, okay.
So anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. So,
okay, אין אונאה לפרוטות. ein ona'ah l'prutos. לוי אמר יש אונאה לפרוטות.
Levi amar yeish ona'ah l'prutos. Yes, even a פרוטה prutah. is אונאה
ona'ah if it's more than one—if it's a sixth of the value.
וכן תני לוי במתניתא, v'chen tani Levi b'matnisa, this is what he
taught in his ברייתא. Baraisa. חמש
פרוטות הן. He had a ברייתא Baraisa that was not like our
משנה, Mishnah. had a different list of the five פרוטות. האונאה פרוטה,
ha'ona'ah pruta, number one, אונאה, ona'ah, which is what we're discussing. והודאה
פרוטה, v'hoda'ah pruta, admission of a מודה במקצת, that was in our
משנה. Mishnah. וקידושי אשה פרוטה, v'kiddushi ishah pruta, which is also in
our משנה. Mishnah, וגזל בפרוטה, v'gezel b'pruta, גזל, gezel, which is presumably
like גזל gezel and the swearing, that's also in our משנה. mishna.
Now, but in opposed to our
משנה, mishnah. which had המציאה, ha'metziah, he had הישיבת הדיינים פרוטה, ha'yeshivas
ha'dayanim pruta, that a court case will meet even over one פרוטה.
prutah, You have to imagine what that is. A פרוטה prutah? really,
I think I did the math once, like in today's money it's
like an eighth of a penny or something like that. Even if
you do the מודה במקצת case... well, no, but you have to
swear... yeah, no, מודה במקצת has other criteria. But if I say
that you owe me a פרוטה, prutah. you—you—it's stolen, there's a loan,
whatever it is, we'll have a court case on it. You have
to remember a פרוטה prutah. is—I think I did the math once—like
in today's money it's like an eighth of a penny or something
like that, even if you do a penny, even if
you do... I think it's general $1,000. Really? For small... no, you
can go for small claims
several
thousand. You can go for small claims, I'm sure for like $50
or something like that. Anyway, okay, the תנא דידן *Tana Didan*, somebody
will look it up. The תנא דידן *Tana Didan* anyway, so anyway,
so he has אונאה *Ona*, so we know that that was debated,
we're claiming that our משנה mishnah. *Mishna* doesn't hold of אונאה *Ona*
being a פרוטה prutah? *prutah*, but he has דיינים *Dayanim* and our
משנה Mishnah *Mishna* has מציאה *metziah*. So we have to figure out
what that debate is about. ותנא דידן מאי טעמא מאי טעמא לא
תנא ישיבת הדיינים *VeTana Didan mai taama mai taama lo tana yeshivat
hadayanim*? Why did our תנא *Tana* not mention a court case is
a פרוטה prutah *prutah*, a court case will hear it? The גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says תני ליה גזל *tani leh gezel*, so because once
you say that גזל *gezel* is a פרוטה prutah. *prutah*, you're basically
saying, you know, if גזל *gezel* is a פרוטה prutah. *prutah*, that
means that you can then sue for it if somebody's considered to
be a גזלן *gazlan*, and it means that you're acknowledging that that's
considered money, so presumably it's the same threshold. Okay, so it could
be inferred. So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says ומי לא תני גזל
ותני אבידה *umi lo tani gezel vetani aveida*? The גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*
says, yeah, a lot of this could be inferred, once you say
a פרוטה *prutah* is the minimum definition of money, so you say
גזל *gezel*, you don't have to say אבידה *aveida*, but nevertheless you
said it, so you should have said דיינים *Dayanim*. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says no, הני איצטריכא ליה *hanei itztricha leh*, you needed
both גזל *gezel* and אבידה *aveida*. גזל הגוזל מחבירו שווה פרוטה shaveh
perutah. ונשבע לו יוליכנו אחריו אפילו למדי *Gezel hagozel michavero shaveh prutah
venishba lo yolichenu acharyav afilu leMadai*. It's not just to tell you
that it's considered גזילה *gezeilah* and you transgressed and you have to
give it back, it's to tell you that even though it's only
worth a פרוטה *prutah*, you have to now go run after this
person halfway around the world to return it. Right, למדי *leMadai*. אבידה
המוצא אבידה
שווה
פרוטה חייב chayav
להכריז *Aveida hamotzei aveida shaveh prutah chayav lehachriz*, it's not just to
tell you you have to return it, again it's telling you the
amount of effort you have to expend even though it's only worth
a פרוטה *prutah*, ואף על גב דזל *veaf al gav dezal*. Now,
and now that's what I said but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* adds
another point, it says you have to announce it even if it
by the time it gets around to announcing it, it's no longer
worth a פרוטה *prutah*. You found it was worth a פרוטה *prutah*,
now it's only worth a half a פרוטה *prutah*, the market went
down or whatever, nevertheless the fact that you found it as a
פרוטה *prutah* obligates you to return it. Okay, so therefore yes, it's
true once it's money it's money and we can infer, but there's
still a חידוש *chidush* of running after the guy, announcing it, but
to say that there's a court case that's not a חידוש *chidush*.
וללוי *veleLevi*, although it's so funny because what about all the effort
of the דיינים *Dayanim*? Anyway, וללוי מאי טעמא לא תנא אבידה *veleLevi
mai taama lo tana aveida*? So לוי Levi *Levi*, why did he
not teach אבידה *aveida*? We understand why he wanted to maybe talk
about the court case, maybe make that more explicit, but then tell
the case of אבידה בפרוטה *aveida beprutah*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says תנא ליה גזל *tana leh gezel*, no you can infer it
from גזל *gezel*. Okay, so again why can you infer אבידה *aveida*
from גזל *gezel* and not the court case idea? ומי לא תנא
גזל ותנא ישיבת הדיינים *Umi lo tana gezel vetana yeshivat hadayanim*? If
you can infer from גזל *gezel* that a פרוטה *prutah* is money
and therefore infer ישיבת הדיינים *yeshivat hadayanim*, also infer אבידה *aveida*. No,
ישיבת הדיינים איצטריכא ליה *yeshivat hadayanim itztricha leh*. No, no, there's a
חידוש *chidush* by ישיבת הדיינים *yeshivat hadayanim* which I wouldn't have figured
out, לאפוקי מדרב קטינא *laapokei mid'Rav Katina*, to reject the position of
רב קטינא *Rav Katina*. דאמר de-amar, רב קטינא בית דין beis din
נזקקין אפילו לפחות משווה פרוטה *Deamar רב קטינא Beis Din nizkakin afilu
lefachos mishaveh prutah*, that a בית דין beis din *Beis Din*
will even sit for less than a פרוטה *prutah*. So actually the
חידוש *chidush* here is not that is not that, you know, is
not that even they'll sit for a פרוטה *prutah*, but it's only
up to a פרוטה *prutah*, not less than a פרוטה *prutah* as
against the רב קטינא *Rav Katina*. Well we'll see that in a
minute. וללוי מאי טעמא לא תנא הקדש *veleLevi mai taama lo tana
hekdesh*? Now, the other thing לוי Levi *Levi* didn't have in his
list because he had ישיבת הדיינים *yeshivat hadayanim* instead of גזל *gezel*.
He said גזל *gezel* you could pretty much have inferred, but there's
a חידוש *chidush* by ישיבת הדיינים *yeshivat hadayanim* that it doesn't go
lower than a פרוטה *prutah*. But the other thing לוי Levi *Levi*
doesn't have because לוי Levi, *Levi* had אונאה *Ona*, the other thing
he didn't have was he didn't have הקדש *hekdesh*, okay, that that's
considered a מעילה Me'ilah *meilah*. So why didn't he teach that? And
maybe that's also not so inferable from גזל *gezel*, who knows what
rules apply by הקדש *hekdesh*, like I said maybe it's about הנאה
hana'ah *hana'ah*, maybe it's something else. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
מאי טעמא לא תנא הקדש בחולין קא מיירי בקדשים לא קא מיירי
*mai taama lo tana hekdesh bechullin ka mairi bekodashim lo ka mairi*.
Yeah, because he's not talking about הקדש *hekdesh* issues, he's talking about
you know what do you call it like like you know non-sacred,
mundane, right. אלא תנא דידן דקא מיירי בקדשים *Ela Tana Didan d'ka
mairi bekodashim*, so now but our תנא *Tana* that is talking about
הקדש *hekdesh* issues, why did it stop by מעילה Me'ilah. *meilah*? So
וניתני מעשר maaser בפרוטה *venisni maaser beprutah*, how about מעשר maaser *maaser*,
which is what we talked before, you can only redeem מעשר שני
maaser sheni *maaser sheni* if it's worth a פרוטה *prutah*? כמאן דאמר
אין In, בחומשו פרוטה *keman deamar ein bechumsho prutah*. No, no, this
is the opinion that says that מעשר ma'aser *maaser* you can that
מעשר ma'aser *maaser* the minimum amount to redeem מעשר ma'aser *maaser* is
not a פרוטה *prutah*, right, מעשר *maaser* the minimum amount to be
able to redeem it is more than a פרוטה *prutah*. You have
to be able to have so much מעשר *maaser* that even the
חומש Chomesh *chomesh* would be a פרוטה *prutah*, which means you have
to have ארבע פרוטות *arba prutos* to redeem מעשר *maaser* so the
חומש Chomesh. *chomesh* could be a פרוטה *prutah*. וניתני חומש chomesh, מעשר
פרוטה *venisni chomesh maaser prutah*, so say that הלכה *halacha* that you
can only redeem it if the חומש chomesh. *chomesh* is worth a
פרוטה *prutah*. בקרנא קא מיירי בחומש לא קא מיירי *bekarna ka mairi
bechomesh lo ka mairi*, no we're only talking about principal, we're not
talking about added things, fine. All right, now let's go look at
the teaching of רב כהנא *Rav Kahana*. גופא אמר רב קטינא *Gufa
amar Rav Katina*, I mean רב קטינא *Rav Katina*, בית דין נזקקין
אפילו לפחות משווה פרוטה *Beis Din nizkakin afilu lefachos mishaveh prutah*, even
less than a פרוטה *prutah*, he doesn't tell us how he knows
it. מתיב רבא Rava. ואת אשר חטא מן הקדש ישלם *maysiv Rava
v'asher chata min hakodesh yeshallem*, or that was a person sinned from
the הקדש *hekdesh* he should pay, this is again by מעילה Me'ilah.
*meilah*, לרבות פחות משווה פרוטה pachus mishaveh perutah להישבון *lerabos pachos mishaveh
prutah lehishavon*. So ואת אשר *v'es asher*, I don't know, ואת דריש
*v'es darish* I guess, is that even if it was less? It
says in רש"י Rashi ואת דריש *Rashi v'es darash*, right, לרבות ואת
דריש *lerabos
v'es darash*. Or maybe because it's about תרומה, trumah. what is this
פסוק pasuk by? ואת אשר חטא מן הקודש ישלם וחמישיתו יוסף עליו.
Ve'es asher chata min hakodesh yeshaleim v'chamishiso yoseif alav. אשר הוא, Asher
hu, what's the פסוק? ממה ממצאנו. Mimah mimaseinu.
Yeah, I remember the end of the פסוק too. Oh, thank you.
Because מעילה Me'ilah we just said was a פרוטה, so what is
this? ויקרא Vayikra 5:16.
5:16. ויקרא Vayikra 5:16. 5:16.
Yeah, but what's the context? נפש כי תמעל מעל וחטאה בשגגה מקדשי
ה׳. Nefesh ki simol maal v'chata bishigagah mikodeshei Hashem.
Yeah. So this is מעילה. Me'ilah
This is מעילה. Me'ilah, So it's interesting because we just said מעילה
Me'ilah. was a שווה פרוטה. So what do we mean by this?
לרבות פחות משווה פרוטה להישבע. lerabbos pachus mishaveh perutah lehishavo. Hmm. Okay,
לקודש אין אבל להדיוט לא. lekodesh in aval lehedyot lo. So I
don't know exactly, maybe you don't bring a קרבן, korban ah, maybe
you don't bring a קרבן מעילה Me'ilah פחות משווה פרוטה pachus mishaveh
perutah. but you actually return it פחות משווה פרוטה. pachus mishaveh perutah...
That's probably what it means.
Okay, for returning. ז׳ מעילה ח׳. Zayin Me'ilah ches. Let's see what
the רמב״ם Rambam says. Yeah, it is מעילה, me'ilah. but I bet
it means that you return less than a פרוטה to הקדש but
you probably don't bring a קרבן if it was by less than
a פרוטה. Yeah, let me just quickly look at the רמב״ם. Rambam.
Been a while since I used my little app here for looking
at the רמב״ם. Rambam. Okay, הלכה רמב״ם Rambam משנה תורה, Mishneh Torah,
עבודה Avodah מעילה. me'ilah, I also saw a nice משנה תורה Mishneh
Torah the רמב״ם Rambam last night. Okay, anyway, although they claimed something
was his autograph and it was... telephone? There? They have one with
his... oh you know what they have? I gotta, I gotta say
this. They have a letter first of all that he wrote to
the... to the Jewish communities to raise money for פדיון שבויים pidyon
shvuyim for people that were taken captive by the crusades. Yeah what
do you mean, yeah, actually have what do you mean? It was
reproduced. Oh, reproduced. Yeah, yeah, but they actually also have, you know
the רמב״ם Rambam wrote a famous letter to עובדיה הגר Ovadiah Hager
about how he's whatever, you know, should see him so part of
כלל ישראל. Klal Yisrael. Anyway, apparently this עובדיה הגר Ovadiah Hager written
was like a priest and he converted to Judaism. So they actually,
I never knew this, he wrote a diary עובדיה הגר Ovadiah Hager
or he wrote some type of a memoir and they actually have
a page from his memoir there in the display of this same
עובדיה הגר. Ovadiah Hager. But anyway, okay, so the רמב״ם Rambam says
like this. פרק ז׳ הלכה ח׳. Perek Zayin Halacha Ches. המועל בפחות
משווה פרוטה בין במזיד בין בשגגה משלם את הקרן ואינו חייב חומש
ולא קרבן. Hamoveh bepachus mishaveh perutah bein bemazid bein beshigagah meshaleim es
hakeren v'eino chayiv chomesh v'lo korban. ואילו שאינו לוקה פחות משווה פרוטה
אם היה מזיד. v'ilu she'eino lokah pachus mishaveh perutah im hayah meizid.
So you return it but you don't bring a קרבן. So the
פרוטה is for a קרבן not for the returning. Okay, so for
מעילה even less than a פרוטה you return, ומהישבון u'mishavon לקודש אין,
lekodesh in, yes, for הקדש, אבל להדיוט לא. aval lehedyot lo. So
if you don't have no obligation to return it, how could you
have a ישיבת דיינים yeshivas dayanim if there's no obligation to return
it? So the גמרא Gemara says אלא אי איתמר הכי איתמר. ela
ee itmar hachi itmar. Right. Because there's a certain minimum that we
don't consider to be money. You mean why is it that הקדש
you do consider to be money? What? I don't... That's a good
question. I mean, is it by, you know, is it... yeah, it's
a good question about whether you're returning it as money or whether
you're, you know, or whether it's some and we just saw more
have a different standard of money by הקדש or whether you're returning
it in a conceptually different matter, like it doesn't matter if you
consider it money money. אבל להדיוט לא Aval lehedyot lo is the
catchphrase. No. So how can you say if by a הדיוט hedyot
you don't have to return פחות משווה פרוטה... no legal obligation to
return it to you, but I obviously have a moral obligation to
return it to you, right? Maybe, that's even not so clear. It
just could be that it's like less than recognized, it's like it
doesn't even exist at a certain point. So meaning I know and
you know, both of us know... When I, when I owe my
taxes, you know, you know... but I understand, but I am saying
if my taxes work out to pennies, I can just round off
to the dollar. I don't have to pay the pennies part, right?
There's a certain point where it's like it doesn't even, you know,
we're saying that that we don't even recognize that as an obligation.
I don't know, let's say we figured out something and I owe
you ten percent of some deal we did, right? We have an
agreement and I'll pay you ten percent of the proceeds, and ten
percent works out to like a parcel part of a penny. Do
I owe you that? Now I don't know, Tzvi's gonna tell us
that somebody makes a lot of money because the banks round off
the partial pennies and they make, and they make, and they make
hundreds of thousands of dollars, right, by not, by not giving people
the partial pennies that they are obligated for doing that. Do they?
Yeah. I was gonna say, so much for that. It's like if
you do all partial pennies. I don't know, but I can understand
that it's not considered money yet. Yes. Ah, my last undergraduate telephone
bill had a balance due of one cent. Yeah. And I never
paid it. And I probably still owe it. There you go. Okay,
so anyway so it says, okay let's just, can we just read
the answer? אבל להדיוט לא. Aval lehedyot lo.
So therefore, so how can you say that you have a court
case if there's no obligation to return it? So אלא אי איתמר
הכי איתמר, ela ee itmar hachi itmar, it's what he says. אמר
רב גיטינא, Amar Rav Gittina, הוחזקו בית דין לשווה פרוטה, huchseku beis
din leshaveh perutah,
yes, they'll only start a court case for something for a claim
worth a פרוטה. But if they began the court case worth a
פרוטה... גומרין אפילו פחות משווי פרוטה, gomrin afilu pachas mishvei prutah,
then they will complete it even if at the end of the
day the only balance that's left is less than a פרוטה. So
it turns out that like, okay, we've settled this case but somebody
says, wait, but I still have this claim, or no, it turns
out that I thought he owed me this amount, but in the
end it's only a half a פרוטה. So then they will actually
finish the case. תחילת דין בעינן פרוטה גמר דין לא בעינן פרוטה.
techilas din be'inan prutah gemar din lo be'inan prutah. Only to open
the case, not to end it, which does still raise the question,
because if at the end of the day, right, you're not obligated
to return less than a פרוטה, why are they going to bother
to complete a case on less than a פרוטה? You know, it
could be though that once they begin a case there's some sense
of like justice, you know? There would be some sense of like
perversion of justice that there they are trying to figure out right
and wrong and then, you know, and there might still be some
and therefore, so then like it's framed differently. It's not framed like
you need a monetary claim to sue somebody, we're already in the
process, so therefore to not complete it would be some type of
a compromise of some sense of justice, you know? Whatever it is
the פשט. pshat.
I understand, but I'm just saying if at the end of the
day בית דין says, you know what? Okay, we started, we thought
Michael owed, you know, five פרוטות. Now we did the whole thing
and after we listened to all the claims Michael really only owes
Dove a half of a פרוטה. So the גמר דין gemar din
is you owe me a half of a פרוטה. Really? There could
be a גמר דין gemar din that you owe me a half
of a פרוטה? Like I don't know, like you have to then
pay? So if you steal half פרוטה from me you don't have
to pay, but בית דין can then פוסקן pasken that you... So
I still don't really understand this. Okay
anyway let's take a look now at the next משנה. mishna We
basically have two different lists, right? Yeah exactly, and some things they
agree on and some things they argue about.
Okay, and it seems like there's no minimum amount for small claims
court. Really? There's only maximum amount? Less... you think you could sue
for less than a penny? Well I mean because judge may laugh
you out.
I mean that's what it says.
I mean for things and stuff like that it would be ridiculous
to
do that, right? But you
lose money. For me, but it's the principle of the
thing. Using those principle of
it's usually money. Exactly. Let's see what
רמב"ם Rambam says about this less than a
פרוטה. Let me just see if רמב"ם Rambam says anything interesting. איני
דדיינים יוצאים לדין בפחות משווי פרוטה ואם הוזקקו לשווי פרוטה גומרין שהן
אפילו. inei dedayanim yotzim ledin bapachas mishvei prutah ve'im huzkaku leshvei prutah
gomrim shehen afilu. He just
quotes the גמרא. Gemara, I don't exactly get it. There could be
a
גמר דין gemar din that you pay less than a פרוטה. All
right, let's go on. Okay. חמישה חומשין הן. hamisha chumshin hein. Five
fifths. And this goes back to what we were learning yesterday.
נ"ה. nun hei. Five fifths. There you go, fifty five. Okay in
the Arabic
decimal system, sort of. Okay. חמישה חומשין הן אלו הן. hamisha chumshin
hein elu hein. האוכל תרומה. ha'ochel trumah. If you eat תרומה. trumah
But תרומה's trumah. now
where some of these things are going to really just count as
one. Okay if you eat תרומה בשוגג trumah beshogeg you return it
to the כהן kohen and your fifth, like a lot of this
we already anticipated on yesterday's דף. daf. Okay so תרומה. trumah Now
included in תרומה trumah, is תרומה, trumah תרומת מעשר, trumas maaser, תרומת
מעשר של דמאי. trumas maaser shel demai. So תרומת מעשר trumas maaser
is the tenth of the tenth from the לוי's מעשר or and
תרומת מעשר של דמאי. trumas maaser shel demai. If you take דמאי
demai grain brought from an עם הארץ am ha'aretz you take מעשר
and then you take the tenth of the tenth for the לוי
would. Okay but you do not have the תרומה trumah of דמאי
demai because you don't give תרומה trumah. of דמאי demai because you
assume that everybody has taken תרומה. trumah. So the one thing you
don't have to give from דמאי demai is תרומה. trumah Okay והחלה
והביכורים. vehachallah vehabikurim. And חלה challah which is considered a type of
תרומה trumah and goes to the כהן kohen and ביכורים bikurim which
is considered a type of תרומה trumah goes to the כהן. kohen.
All those things which are by the way five things. Anyway all
of them count as one and if you eat from any of
those בשוגג beshogeg you pay back plus a fifth to the כהן.
kohen. מוסיף חומש. mosif chomesh. So those things you add a fifth.
The reason it repeats the word מוסיף חומש mosif chomesh is because
a couple of these units have multiple things in them. והפודה נטע
רבעי ומעשר שני שלו. vehapodeh neta revai umaaser sheni shelo. If you
redeem your own נטע רבעי neta revai the fourth years plant after
three years of ערלה orlah the fruit there is like מעשר שני
maaser sheni gets brought to ירושלים Yerushalayim and eaten there or you
could redeem it on money or your own מעשר שני maaser sheni
you redeem and it's שלו. shelo. If you redeem somebody else's מעשר
שני maaser sheni or נטע רבעי neta revai you don't add a
fifth. But if the owners redeem their own they add a fifth.
מוסיף חומש. mosif chomesh. So again those were two but they're counting
as one. Okay so that's תרומה terumah, and מעשר שני ma'aser sheni
plus the things associated with it. והנהנה
שווי פרוטה מן ההקדש. vehaneheneh mishvei prutah min hahekdesh. So that's מעילה.
מוסיף חומש. mosif chomesh. Did I skip a line? I skipped a
line. הפודה הקדשו מוסיף חומש. hapodeh hekdesho mosif chomesh. Your own הקדש
again we this is something almost all these we mentioned yesterday. Okay
if you פודה podeh your own הקדש you add a fifth. If
somebody else redeems it then they buy it back from הקדש they
don't add a fifth. והנהנה שווי פרוטה מן vehaneheneh mishvei prutah min
If you get הנאה of a and then you add a fifth,
right? And there's again the שוה פרוטה which we mentioned in the
previous משנה. mishna? Okay, that's מעילה, that's four. והגוזל חברו שוה פרוטה
ונשבע לו מוסיף חומש. ve-ha-gozel chaveiro shaveh prutah ve-nishba lo mosif chomesh.
If you swear falsely to somebody that you don't owe them money
and you do, and then you admit to it, you bring a
special קרבן and you add a fifth when you return it. So
we pretty much mentioned all of these yesterday, so that was a
nice preview of today's משנה. mishna. Let's take a look now at
the גמרא. Gemara אמר
רבא, Amar Rava, said רבא. קשיא ליה לרבי אלעזר. Kashya leh le-Rabbi
Elazar. Rabbi Elazar was bothered. תרומת מעשר של דמאי. Terumat ma'aser shel
demai. So why is this that by תרומת מעשר של דמאי terumat
ma'aser shel demai if you eat it, you add a fifth? וכי
עשו חכמים חיזוק לדבריהם כשל תורה? Ve-chi asu chachamim chizuk le-divreihem ke-shel
Torah?
You know, why, is it really possible, meaning I get that we're
going to treat דמאי, demai, you know, you're חייב to be מפריש,
mafrish, we'll have all these דרבנן de-rabbanan דינים, dinim, but would we
really go so far to say that you have to add a
fifth? Okay, now you might remember yesterday there was a whole question
about when you're פודה מעשר שני של דמאי, podeh ma'aser sheni shel
demai, you don't add a fifth, right? And that was the גמרא's
Gemara proof that the fifth was considered to be separate and not
part of the פדיון, pidyon, but an add-on to the פדיון. pidyon.
So here he's saying the same type of a question. Would they
really treat דמאי demai so weighty that if you ate it, you'd
have to add a fifth? Are they going to treat it like
a דאורייתא? de-oraita? כשל תורה? Ke-shel Torah? תרומת מעשר, Terumat ma'aser, this
is the donation the לוי gives to a כהן? kohen? Right. So
the כהן kohen is eating this which was, which came from דמאי?
demai? Yeah, that's okay, but somebody else ate it rather than the
כהן. kohen. The idea of adding a fifth is if a non-כהן
kohen eats תרומה, terumah they add a fifth. Yeah, right, so a
non-כהן kohen ate תרומת מעשר של דמאי. terumat ma'aser shel demai. And
so the question is, I bought דמאי, demai, I gave the מעשר
from the דמאי demai to my friend Michael here who's a לוי,
he takes a tenth of that tenth and gives it to David
here who's a כהן, kohen, okay, but then, you know, Jenna comes
and she's over at David's house and doesn't realize that it's תרומה
terumah and she eats it. She eats תרומה terumah Cheerios. Yeah, תרומה
Cheerios, yeah. So she goes and she has to now give back
a fifth, okay? וכי עשו חכמים חיזוק לדבריהם כשל תורה? Ve-chi asu
chachamim chizuk le-divreihem ke-shel Torah? אמר רב נחמן אמר שמואל, Amar Rav
Nachman amar Shmuel, הא מני רבי מאיר היא. ha mani Rabbi Meir
hi. Yeah, it's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. דאמר עשו חכמים חיזוק לדבריהם
כשל תורה. De-amar asu chachamim chizuk le-divreihem ke-shel Torah. Sometimes the rabbis
go, go do it so weightily that they treat it as if
it is a דאורייתא. de-oraita. Now before we get further, what type
of a question is this? Of course, sometimes the rabbis give things
a lot of weight as if it's a דאורייתא. de-oraita. So some
of it might be what we talked yesterday, that we already know
for example that when you're פודה מעשר שני של דמאי, podeh ma'aser
sheni shel demai, you don't add a fifth. And that's very parallel.
מעשר שני של דמאי, Ma'aser sheni shel demai, תרומת מעשר של דמאי,
terumat ma'aser shel demai, if you don't add a fifth here, why
do you add a fifth here? So maybe that's in the background.
But of course, the רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir example we're going to
bring has nothing to do with anything about מעשר or a fifth.
Let's see what the רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is. דתניא, De-tanya, we
learned in a ברייתא, braita, המביא גט ממדינת הים. ha-mevi get mi-medinat
ha-yam. If you bring a גט get from overseas. נתנו לה ולא
אמר לה בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם. Netano lah ve-lo amar lah bifnai
nichtav u-vifnai nechtam. You give it to the woman and you don't
say I'm the שליח, shaliach, it was signed and sealed in front
of me, signed and, you know, written and signed in front of
me. So which is what you're obligated to do to ensure that
it was done לשמה lishmah and that it wasn't a forgery. יוציא
והולד ממזר דברי רבי מאיר. Yotzi ve-ha-valad mamzer divrei Rabbi Meir. Rabbi
Meir
says you treat it as completely an invalid גט, get, even though
it was only a rabbinic issue that wasn't being addressed. And if
she's remarried and she's had kids, I don't care, she has to
get divorced from the second guy and the kids are ממזרים. mamzerim.
וחכמים אומרים, Va-chachamim omrim, no, אין הולד ממזר, ein ha-valad mamzer, we
are not going to treat the kids as ממזרים. mamzerim. Now תוספות
Tosafot, points out the fact that they don't say לא יוציא lo
yotzi but they just say אין הולד ממזר, ein ha-valad mamzer, sounds
like חכמים chachamim would still say that you have to get divorced,
okay, but we don't treat the kids as ממזרים. mamzerim. כיצד יעשה?
Keitzad ya'aseh? Now
what should you do in order to make it good? Okay, now
at what stage, יטלנו הימנה ויחזור ויתננו לה, yitlenu himena ve-yachzor ve-yitnenu
lah, use the שליח, shaliach, take it back from her and then
give it again בפני שנים bifnai shenayim in front of two, ויאמר
לה בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם, ve-yomar lah bifnai nichtav u-vifnai nechtam, it
was written and signed in front of me. So רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir goes so overboard there, presumably he'd go overboard here too and
say that we treat it as a full דאורייתא. de-oraita. Now let's
look at תוספות. וכי עשו חכמים, Ve-chi asu chachamim, to understand what
type of a question this is. וכי עשו חכמים חיזוק לדבריהם כשל
תורה. Ve-chi asu chachamim chizuk le-divreihem ke-shel Torah. אף על גב, Af
al gav, says תוספות, דבכמה מקומות עשו, de-ve-chama mekomot asu, אפילו יותר
משל תורה. afilu yoter mi-shel Torah. Sometimes of course we treat it
as a תורה, Torah sometimes even stricter. היינו היכא דשייך למקנס. Hainu
heicha de-shayach le-miknas. That's when there's a logic to add lots of
סייג, seyag, we're trying to protect something, you know, and so on.
אבל הכא אפילו בתרומת מעשר ודאי לא הוה שייך למקנס חומש Aval
hacha afilu be-terumat ma'aser vadai lo havah shayach le-miknas chomesh אם לא
שאמרה תורה. im lo she-amrah Torah. Here the whole idea of adding
a fifth is only because the תורה Torah insists, like the whole
demand is not, you know, seems like already a fine that the
תורה's Torah adding. ולהכי לא הוה ליה למקנס בשל דמאי. U-le-hachi lo
havah leh le-miknas be-shel demai. So therefore if we're just doing a
rabbinic thing, since the whole תורה is giving a fine, why would
we have to continue this idea of a fine at a rabbinic
level? Okay, so that's his question. Excellent point, meaning because he treats
it as a fine, so we're continuing it. I understand, but the
point is that whatever, תוספות understands that makes sense when the thing
seems to have some intrinsic value. Something that itself is just a
fine, doesn't, that's at least how he explains why the גמרא's Gemara
a little bothered. Okay, I would have added like I said that
we know by מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni, that you don't add a
fifth by דמאי. demai. Okay, ומשני דהכא נמי עשו הולד ממזר. u-mishanei
de-hacha nami asu ha-valad mamzer. Okay, but look at the way רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir was so extreme in the גט get case. אף
על פי שאין סברא אלא משום דאשתו. Af al pi she-ein sevara
ela mishum de-ishto. Even though there's no real concern that we're addressing.
I mean, there's no logic between saying whatever we're trying to protect
with בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם Befani Nichtav u-vefani Nechtam warrants saying הולד
ממזר. Ha-velad mamzer. But the point is it doesn't matter whether it
warrants it or not. The point is, you treat it like it's
a Torah problem. So the same way רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir did
that by a גט, Get, you know, we're going to do the
same thing here too as well. Even though there's no real concern
that we're addressing, I mean, there's no logic between saying whatever we're
trying to protect with בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם Befani Nichtav u-vefani Nechtam
warrants saying הולד ממזר. Ha-velad mamzer. But the point is it doesn't
matter whether it warrants it or not. The point is, you treat
it like it's a Torah problem. So the same way רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir did that by a גט, Get, you know, we're going
to do the same thing here too as well. Even though there's
no real concern that we're addressing, I mean, there's no logic between
saying whatever we're trying to protect with בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם Befani
Nichtav u-vefani Nechtam warrants saying הולד ממזר. Ha-velad mamzer. But the point
is it doesn't matter whether it warrants it or not. The point
is, you treat it like it's a Torah problem. So the same
way רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir did that by a גט, Get, you
know, we're going to do the same thing here too as well.
Even though there's no real concern that we're addressing, I mean, there's
no logic between saying whatever we're trying to protect with בפני נכתב
ובפני נחתם Befani Nichtav u-vefani Nechtam warrants saying הולד ממזר. Ha-velad mamzer.
But the point is it doesn't matter whether it warrants it or
not. The point is you treat it like it's a Torah problem.
So the same way רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir did that by a
גט, Get, you know, we're going to do the same thing here
too as well. Even though there's no logic that warrants being strict,
the question is what made you so strict? What made me so
strict? Like Michael said, you know, we apply it as if this
is the Torah law. Once we say it's a Rabbinic requirement, we
treat it like it's a Torah requirement. I don't care if there's
a logic for this severity or not. Okay, so that's what we're
saying with רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Now
the גמרא Gemara says like this, לרבי מאיר, Le-Rabbi Meir, but now
the גמרא Gemara pushes back. לרבי מאיר משום דלא אמר לה בפני
נכתב ובפני נחתם. Le-Rabbi Meir mishum delo amar lah Befani Nichtav u-vefani
Nechtam. Now you see תוספות's point. Really, this is a little out
of proportion, isn't it? Just because you didn't say that, יוציא והולד
ממזר? Yotzi ve-ha-velad mamzer? You're going to go so far? I mean,
that's very harsh. I mean, much harsher than adding a fifth. הולד
ממזר? Ha-velad mamzer? אין, yes, רבי מאיר לטעמיה, Rabbi Meir l'ta'ameh, דאמר,
Rabbi Meir goes according to his reasoning, דאמר רב המנונא משמיה דעולא
אמר היה רבי מאיר כל המשנה ממטבע שטבעו חכמים בגיטין יוציא והולד
ממזר. De-amar Rav Hamnuna mishmeih de-Ulla amar hayah Rabbi Meir kol ha-meshaneh
mi-matbe'a she-tav'u Chachamim be-gittin yotzi ve-ha-velad mamzer.
Anytime you change any of the sort of the coin, notice the
word מטבע, Matbe'a, right, you know, any of the coinage that the
חכמים Chachamim had stamped, like any of the exact formula the חכמים
Chachamim had instituted by גט, Get, so you know, we treat it
like completely פסול גט, Pasul get, even if it was only a
trivial problem and the kid is a ממזר. Mamzer. Now, of course
you could say that that language reflects, yes, a very harsh approach
of רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, but only maybe specifically by גיטין. Gittin.
Maybe he's very, very strict at אשת איש, Eshet ish, we want
to make sure everybody does it accordingly. We're now making that even
more general and saying that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir always treats sort
of like every Rabbinic thing as if it's exactly a דאורייתא De-Oraita
problem no matter how harsh the consequence. I'm surprised Thomas didn't say,
since he's giving גוזמא, Guzma, that's also a possibility, right? What's גוזמא?
Guzma? הולד ממזר? Ha-velad mamzer? No, if the חכמים Chachamim say back
there's no real... right, there's no real חשש. Chashash. Nobody's going to
say הולד ממזר Ha-velad mamzer when we're talking about real issues of
אשת איש Eshet ish if they don't mean it. And the חכמים
Chachamim say back אין הולד ממזר. Ein ha-velad mamzer. So we're clearly
nobody's exaggerating here. Right, okay, I mean,
sometimes that's used, right, in order to give an... to understand the...
I don't think so. הולד ממזר Ha-velad mamzer in... not in this
context. Yeah, but I don't know in personal status cases. הולד ממזר
Ha-velad mamzer is... I mean Rabbinicly ממזר, Mamzer, but we mean it
when we say it. Yeah. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay,
now fine. So whatever. So whether we can compare it to this
extreme case of הולד ממזר, Ha-velad mamzer, we're saying I get it,
it's only Rabbinic, but nevertheless we're going to say the author of
our משנה mishna is רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and he's very strict
and he says you add a חומש chomesh. even by תרומת מעשר
Terumat ma'aser of דמאי. Demai. Now
מתיב רב ששת. Metiv Rav Sheshet. Now רב ששת Rav Sheshet asks
on this. מחללו כסף על כסף. Mechalelo kesef al kesef. Now we're
going to talk here about
money of like of
מעשר שני, Ma'aser Sheni okay, of דמאי. Demai. Now you have money
of מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni of דמאי. Demai. Now we're going to
see in a little bit that if it's money of ודאי Vadai
of מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni, of ודאי, Vadai, normal מעשר שני, Ma'aser
Sheni there's certain limits in terms of how you can transfer money
to money. But money of מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni, of דמאי, Demai,
we're more... we have more latitude of transferring money to money. Okay,
so מחללו כסף על כסף נחושת על נחושת, Mechalelo kesef al kesef,
nechoshet al nechoshet, you can go from silver coins to silver coins,
copper to copper, כסף על נחושת, Kesef al nechoshet, silver to copper,
ונחושת על פירות, Ve-nechoshet al peirot,
and copper onto fruit.
Apparently you can't go from copper onto silver, although that's a little
bit strange you would think you can go up. Anyway, ויחזור ויפדה
את הפירות, Ve-yachzor ve-yifdeh et ha-peirot,
and you can go ahead and redeem the פירות Peirot even after
you've transferred it to fruit you're out of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. You say,
well now it's back to fruit, you have to bring the fruit
to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So no, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that you
can go back and put the... and come from the fruit back
onto money, onto coins. דברי רבי מאיר. Divrei Rabbi Meir. That's what
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. וחכמים אומרים, Ve-Chachamim omrim, and the חכמים
Chachamim say יעלו פירות ויאכלו בירושלים. Ya'alu peirot ve-yei'achlu bi-Yerushalayim. No, once
it's on fruit you have to eat them in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So
the point about this is to point out that we're trying to
claim that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is more strict about
דמאי, Demai, right, so and he's the one that says that you
have to add a חומש. chomesh? But here רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
looks like he's being more lenient about דמאי. Demai. He is letting
you go from the fruit back to money and the חכמים Chachamim
are not letting you go back from the fruit to the money.
Okay, so now but first of all the גמרא, now the גמרא's
going to point out, I'm going to read this like תוספות, that
don't think that this is an issue, oh maybe רבי מאיר's Rabbi
Meir more lenient because it's דמאי. Demai. Maybe in general רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir has more latitude about how you can transfer money to
money and fruit to money. Maybe this has nothing to do with
דמאי. Demai. The גמרא's going to... no, I'm going to show you
that if it's normal מעשר שני, maaser sheni then the rules are
not so liberal. But because it's דמאי, Demai, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
is being more lenient. So that proves the opposite of your argument.
Your argument was רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is stricter than the חכמים
Chachamim about דמאי. Demai. Here it looks like... Now let me show
you that this is because it's דמאי demai and not just a
general issue about how you can transfer money. To be clear on
the facts, so I've gone to ירושלים Yerushalayim and I've bought, I've
bought the פירות peirot in ירושלים Yerushalayim and now I can't eat
anymore and I want to go home. The question is can I
then transfer? No, once it's in ירושלים Yerushalayim you can't transfer it.
This is that it's outside of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. That's why it says
יעלו לירושלים. ya'alu l'Yerushalayim. Okay,
if it's you, right. Okay, but now, but let's just show that
this issue about רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir being more lenient is specifically
because it's דמאי. demai. So now the גמרא continues, says like
this, והתנן. ve-hatnan. Okay, wait a minute, יביא ומחללין כסף על נחושת.
yavi ve-mechalelin kessef al nechoshet. Now normally you can't go from כסף
to
נחושת, nechoshet, okay? דתנן, de-hatnan, we taught,
סלע של מעשר שני, sela shel maaser sheni, this is ודאי מעשר
שני, vadai maaser sheni, which is silver. שנתערבו, she-nitarvu, so you got
mixed up a coin of מעשר שני maaser sheni, money and of
חולין chullin money and you don't know which is which. Okay? So
what you want to do is, you could just go spend both
of those coins as if they're מעשר שני, maaser sheni, but you'd
rather only spend one סלע worth of מעשר שני, maaser sheni, not
both. So you would say the most normal thing to do is
take another סלע of my, and say whichever one of these two
coins is מעשר שני, maaser sheni that value is transferred onto this.
Okay, guess what you would do. And then you have this thing
is definitely and those two are free. The only thing is, is
that we're going to see you cannot do silver to silver. So
what, in order to do it, you're going to have to take
a different type of a coin. Okay, because if it's basically silver
and silver and it's a סלע on a סלע, it's not really
like a פדיון, pidyon, that's all like equivalent. A פדיון pidyon suggests
that there's something different, like it's transferring to a different type of
a thing. Okay, so here's what you have to do. Okay, מביא
סלע מעות, mevi sela maot, you bring מעות, maot, which actually רש"י
Rashi says here is copper, which I don't really get because רש"י
says here the איסר issar is a silver and it said that
everything up to here is a silver till here is copper. So
I don't know, maybe there's copper מעות maot as well. Don't ask
me. Anyway you bring the stuff that's copper, okay,
or maybe these are very big copper coins and these are very
tiny silver coins, I have no idea. Anyway, okay, מביא סלע מעות,
mevi sela maot, you bring copper coins, ואומר כל מקום שיש סלע
של מעשר שני, ve-omer kol makom she-yesh sela shel maaser sheni,
whichever one of those two coins is a מעשר שני maaser sheni
coin, מחוללות על מעות הללו, mechulalot al maot halalu,
is transferred onto these copper coins, ובורר את היפה שבהן ומחללו עליה.
u-borer et hayafe she-bahen u-mechallo aleiha.
And then now that I've got this pile of copper coins, I
don't want to bring copper coins to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. First of all
they're rough, second of all it takes a lot more to fit
in a lot of those pennies in my pocket than one silver
coin. So then of these two coins that got mixed up, I
say okay this is the nicer one, you know, it's the one
that's more full or whatever, you know, it's newer. So that now,
now that these two coins are both חולין chullin because I've transferred
the value of the מעשר שני maaser sheni to this copper, now
the value of these copper coins is transferred to this back to
this nice silver coin that got mixed up. You got it? So
you transfer off and on. What you really could do is, you
know, if you have these two coins and you don't know which
is which, right, you really in theory could just take one and
say if this is the מעשר שני maaser sheni good, and if
it's not the מעשר שני maaser sheni then this is transferred to
this. But you can't go same to same, silver to silver. So
I don't know, that's because that's considered not to be a פדיון,
pidyon, that's considered like, you know,
פדיון pidyon suggests that there's some difference between what you're going from
and to. I don't really get it, but that's the idea. So
what you do is you take all these like copper coins, okay,
and you say whichever one of these is it's now transferred here.
You know it's not the same value? What? It is the same
value. It's equal to, it's copper coins worth one silver coin. Now
this has the קדושה, neither of these do. Now you take the
nicer one of these and now you say now I'm going to
transfer back. Okay, as long as it's different, silver to copper. And
you add a חומש, chomesh. right? What? You have to add a
חומש. That's a good question. Wait, presumably you would have to add
a חומש. Yeah, it's a good point, we're not saying that but
presumably you'd have to. What? Why? Because you're פודה מעשר שני. podeh
maaser sheni. Second generation, you've already done that in the first. Yes,
so second generation doesn't add a חומש? What we said before that
was by הקדש, but by מעשר שני ma'aser sheni second generation actually
you do add a
חומש. So that's a good point. I think so, I think so.
ויסף
חמישיתו, ve-yasaf chamishito, yeah, yeah, so exactly. Anyway, so the גמרא says,
alright but moving on, okay that was a good point. כל מקום
שיש סלע של מעשר שני מחוללות על מעות הללו ובורר את היפה
שבהן ומחללו עליה, kol makom she-yesh sela shel maaser sheni mechulalot al
maot halalu u-borer et hayafe she-bahen u-mechallo aleiha, מפני שאמרו, mipnei she-amru,
and here you go, Janice you asked why, this isn't going to
say why but this is going to say what. Okay, they said:
מחללין אותו כסף על נחושת מדוחק. mechalelin oto kessef al nechoshet midochek.
You can go from כסף to נחושת nechoshet like in an urgent
situation. ולא שיתקיים כן, ve-lo she-itkayem ken, and even when we allow
that, it's not that it should end up as נחושת, nechoshet, like
because that's like going down and stuff that'll, you know whatever, get
rusty sooner. אלא שיחזור ויחלל על כסף. ela she-yachzor ve-yechalel al kessef.
In order to get back to silver. תני מיהו, tani mihu, nevertheless
what we hear from here is מחלל מדוחק. mechalel midochek.
That when do we allow you to go from כסף to נחושת,
nechoshet, only in an urgent situation. מדוחק אין דלא מדוחק כלל, midochek
in d'lo midochek klal, only in urgent. So now let's go back
to the case of מעשר שני של דמאי. ma'aser sheni shel demai.
What did we say by מעשר שני של דמאי? ma'aser sheni shel
demai? We said that רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir let you go from
silver to copper and copper to silver and from silver to the
פירות peros whatever copper to the פירות. peros. So number one it
was clear there that we were being more lenient because it was
דמאי. demai. And רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir was being more lenient than
the חכמים. chachamim. So you see that ברייתא braisa we talked earlier
was a leniency of דמאי. demai. And רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir was
more lenient than the חכמים chachamim by דמאי. demai. So how can
you say in our משנה where we say that you add a
fifth when it's תרומת מעשר terumas ma'aser of דמאי, demai, that that's
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir who's stricter by דמאי? demai? You know, because
it's rabbinic and it's stricter. You got the point? The question is
why are we so strict by תרומת מעשר terumas ma'aser of דמאי
demai you add a fifth? And it's רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, he's
strict by all these rabbinic things. Well here we see by מעשר
שני ma'aser sheni of דמאי, demai, okay it's not תרומת מעשר terumas
ma'aser but it's מעשר שני ma'aser sheni, of דמאי, demai, that רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir is more lenient and he allows you to go
from the thing to the fruit and the fruit to the thing
and whatever. So how can you say he's more strict in our
משנה? So the גמרא's answer is אמר רב יוסף אף על פי
שמיקל רבי מאיר בפדיונו, Amar Rav Yosef af al pi she-meikel Rebbi
Meir b'pidyono, even though he is lenient by these issues of redeeming
מעשר שני, ma'aser sheni okay, מחמיר הוא באכילתו, machmir hu b'achilaso, he's
strict when it comes to eating תרומת מעשר terumas ma'aser of דמאי
demai because when you eat תרומת מעשר terumas ma'aser you're doing a
sin, right? A non-כהן Kohen eating תרומת מעשר. terumas ma'aser. So there
the issue of adding a fifth is basically like a type of
a כפרה kapparah thing. You've done this sin, you ate it. Okay,
it's only rabbinic but it's תרומת מעשר terumas ma'aser of דמאי, demai,
I'm going to make you add a fifth even though it's only
rabbinic. But talking about בפודה b'podeh מעשר שני of דמאי, demai, we're
not talking about having transgressed, so in that case I can be
more lenient. Okay?
So we will, so let's just read the one example about this,
דתניא, d'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braisa, לא התירו למכור דמאי
אלא לסיטון בלבד. lo hitiru limkor demai ela l'siton bilvad.
Are you allowed to sell דמאי? demai? You bought דמאי demai and
now can you resell it with like, I'm a middleman or whatever,
can I buy it from one עם הארץ am ha'aretz and resell
it or do I have to think that if I'm going to
resell it, people are going to assume since I'm a חבר chaver
that I took תרומות ומעשרות terumos u'ma'asros and therefore
they're not going to take it? Maybe as soon as it gets
to my hand, even if all I'm interested in doing is reselling
it and making a profit, as soon as I get possession maybe
I have to be מפריש mafrish תרומות ומעשרות. terumos u'ma'asros. So that's
the question. Did they let me resell דמאי demai without taking תרומות
ומעשרות? terumos u'ma'asros? So the only person they let do it was
a סיטון. siton. A סיטון siton is basically a, I don't know
what you call him, a wholesaler? Yeah, like he basically he buys
up from all the producers and then he goes ahead and he
like, he you know and he resells it to like whatever, all
the store owners or whatever, he sells in large quantities. Everybody knows
that this guy isn't being מפריש. mafrish. This guy is basically just
buying it up and then reselling it, okay? Him they let not
be מפריש. mafrish. ובעל הבית, u'ba'al habayis, but if it's a homeowner,
בין כך ובין כך צריך לעשר דברי רבי מאיר. bein kach u'vein
kach tzarich l'aser divrei Rebbi Meir. Whether you're selling in small quantities
or large quantities you have to take מעשר before you resell it.
וחכמים אומרים, v'chachamim omrim, and the חכמים chachamim say, אחד סיטון ואחד
בעל הבית מוכר ומשלח לחברו, echad siton v'echad ba'al habayis mocher u'meshale'ach
l'chavero, whether you're a סיטון siton or whether you're a homeowner, even
if you're a homeowner the way the גמרא explains it elsewhere, but
you're buying and selling in large quantities, you can go ahead and
buy and sell, ונותן לו במתנה v'nosin lo b'matana or even give
as a gift, ואינו חושש v'eino choshesh and you don't have to
be מפריש mafrish תרומות ומעשרות, terumos u'ma'asros, people understand that you just
bought and resold. How is it relevant? It's relevant because רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir is more strict here, right? He only, he limits because
why is he more strict? He's afraid that if you buy from
a homeowner you'll think he took תרומות ומעשרות terumos u'ma'asros and you'll
come to eat it. So what is he being strict about? He's
being strict that he doesn't want people to accidentally eat דמאי. demai.
Right? That's the stringency. So when it comes to an issue of
eating it in a wrong way, you're going to eat this thing,
it's דמאי, demai, you're going to think it's תרומות ומעשרות terumos u'ma'asros
and it's not. You're going to eat תרומת מעשר terumas ma'aser of
דמאי demai and you sinned and you have to now ahead pay
back the money. So when it's about the עבירה aveira of eating
it, he's going to be strict. When it's about how to do
the פדיון, pidyon, he's going to be more lenient. Okay? So now
we've explained our משנה. וחכמים מתנה? v'chachamim matana? I don't know. So
now we've explained that the משנה that says תרומת מעשר terumas ma'aser
you add a fifth even though it's only rabbinic, that's רבי מאיר.
Rebbi Meir. רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir is strict when it comes to
transgressions of eating דמאי demai improperly even if at times he'll be
lenient when it comes to how you do the פדיון pidyon of
דמאי. demai.